<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="ceki at qos ddoott ch ">Ceki Gulcu</author>
    <title>Home</title>
  </properties>


<body>

  <h1>Simple Logging Facade for Java (SLF4J)</h1>

  <p>The Simple Logging Facade for Java or (SLF4J) is intended to
  serve as a simple facade for various logging APIs allowing to the
  end-user to plug in the desired implementation at
  <em>deployment</em> time. SLF4J also allows for a <a
  href="manual.html#gradual">gradual migration path</a> away from
  Jakarta Commons Logging (JCL).
  </p>

  <p>Logging API implementations can either choose to implement the
  the SLF4J interfaces directly, e.g. <a
  href="http://logback.qos.ch">logback</a> or <a
  href="api/org/slf4j/impl/SimpleLogger.html">SimpleLogger</a>. Alternatively,
  it is possible (and rather easy) to write SLF4J adapters for the
  given API implementation, e.g. <a
  href="api/org/slf4j/impl/Log4jLoggerAdapter.html">Log4jLoggerAdapter</a>
  or <a
  href="api/org/slf4j/impl/JDK14LoggerAdapter.html">JDK14LoggerAdapter</a>..
  </p>

  <h2>Simplicity</h2>

  <p>The SLF4J interfaces and their various adapters are simple and
  straightforward. Most developers familiar with the Java language
  should be able to read and fully understand the code in less than
  one hour.
  </p>

  <p>SLF4J does not rely on any special class loader machinery. In
  fact, the binding between SLF4J and a given logging API
  implementation is performed <em>statically</em> at compile time of
  each binding. Each binding is hardwired to use one and only specific
  logging API implementation. Each binding corresponds to one jar
  file. In your code, you simply drop the binding of your choice, that
  is a jar file, onto the appropriate class path location. As a
  consequence of this simple approach, SLF4J suffers from none of the
  class loader problems or memory leaks observed with Jakarta Commons
  Logging (JCL).
  </p>

  <p>We hope that simplicity of the SLF4J interfaces and the deployment
  model will make it easy for developers of other logging APIs to
  conform to the SLF4J model.
  </p>

</body>
</document>

